In a hundred years? Two hundred years? And these are three really profound changes that are not, like, future stuff.
¿Dentro de 100 años? ¿Doscientos años? Y estos son tres cambios muy profundos que no son cosas del futuro.
This is stuff we take for granted today. So this lifecode stuff turns out to be a superpower. It turns out to be this incredibly powerful way of changing viruses, of changing plants, of changing animals, perhaps even of evolving ourselves. It's something that Steve Gullans and I have been thinking about for a while. Let's have some risks. Like every powerful technology, like electricity, like an automobile, like computers, this stuff potentially can be misused. And that scares a lot of people. And as you apply these technologies, you can even turn human beings into chimeras. Remember the Greek myth where you mix animals? Well, some of these treatments actually end up changing your blood type. Or they'll put male cells in a female body or vice versa, which sounds absolutely horrible until you realize, the reason you're doing that is you're substituting bone marrow during cancer treatments. So by taking somebody else's bone marrow, you may be changing some fundamental aspects of yourself, but you're also saving your life. And as you're thinking about this stuff, here's something that happened 20 years ago. This is Emma Ott. She's a recent college admittee. She's studying accounting. She played two varsity sports. She graduated as a valedictorian. And that's not particularly extraordinary, except that she's the first human being born to three parents. Why? Because she had a deadly mitochondrial disease that she might have inherited. So when you swap out a third person's DNA and you put it in there, you save the lives of people. But you also are doing germline engineering, which means her kids, if she has kids, will be saved and won't go through this. And [their] kids will be saved, and their grandchildren will be saved, and this passes on. That makes people nervous. So 20 years ago, the various authorities said, why don't we study this for a while? There are risks to doing stuff, and there are risks to not doing stuff, because there were a couple dozen people saved by this technology, and then we've been thinking about it for the next 20 years. So as we think about it, as we take the time to say, "Hey, maybe we should have longer studies, maybe we should do this, maybe we should do that," there are consequences to acting, and there are consequences to not acting. Like curing deadly diseases -- which, by the way, is completely unnatural. It is normal and natural for humans to be felled by massive epidemics of polio, of smallpox, of tuberculosis. When we put vaccines into people, we are putting unnatural things into their body because we think the benefit outweighs the risk. Because we've built unnatural plants, unnatural animals, we can feed about seven billion people. We can do things like create new life-forms. And as you create new life-forms, again, that sounds terribly scary and terribly bothersome, until you realize that those life-forms live on your dining room table. Those flowers you've got on your dining room table -- there's not a lot that's natural about them, because people have been breeding the flowers to make this color, to be this size, to last for a week. You don't usually give your loved one wildflowers because they don't last a whole lot of time. What all this does is it flips Darwin completely on his head. See, for four billion years, what lived and died on this planet depended on two principles: on natural selection and random mutation. And so what lived and died, what was structured, has now been flipped on its head. And what we've done is created this completely parallel evolutionary system where we are practicing unnatural selection and non-random mutation. So let me explain these things. This is natural selection. This is unnatural selection. (Laughter) So what happens with this stuff is, we started breeding wolves thousands of years ago in central Asia to turn them into dogs. And then we started turning them into big dogs and into little dogs. But if you take one of the chihuahuas you see in the Hermès bags on Fifth Avenue and you let it loose on the African plain, you can watch natural selection happen. (Laughter) Few things on Earth are less natural than a cornfield. You will never, under any scenario, walk through a virgin forest and see the same plant growing in orderly rows at the same time, nothing else living there. When you do a cornfield, you're selecting what lives and what dies. And you're doing that through unnatural selection. It's the same with a wheat field, it's the same with a rice field. It's the same with a city, it's the same with a suburb. In fact, half the surface of Earth has been unnaturally engineered so that what lives and what dies there is what we want, which is the reason why you don't have grizzly bears walking through downtown Manhattan. How about this random mutation stuff? Well, this is random mutation. This is Antonio Alfonseca. He's otherwise known as the Octopus, his nickname. He was the Relief Pitcher of the Year in 2000. And he had a random mutation that gave him six fingers on each hand, which turns out to be really useful if you're a pitcher. (Laughter) How about non-random mutation? A non-random mutation is beer. It's wine. It's yogurt. How many times have you walked through the forest and found all-natural cheese? Or all-natural yogurt? So we've been engineering this stuff. Now, the interesting thing is, we get to know the stuff better. We found one of the single most powerful gene-editing instruments, CRISPR, inside yogurt. And as we start engineering cells, we're producing eight out of the top 10 pharmaceutical products, including the stuff that you use to treat arthritis, which is the number one best-selling drug, Humira. So this lifecode stuff. It really is a superpower. It really is a way of programming stuff, and there's nothing that's going to change us more than this lifecode. So as you're thinking of lifecode, let's think of five principles as to how we start guiding, and I'd love you to give me more. So, principle number one: we have to take responsibility for this stuff. The reason we have to take responsibility is because we're in charge. These aren't random mutations. This is what we are doing, what we are choosing. It's not, "Stuff happened." It didn't happen at random. It didn't come down by a verdict of somebody else. We engineer this stuff, and it's the Pottery Barn rule: you break it, you own it. Principle number two: we have to recognize and celebrate diversity in this stuff. There have been at least 33 versions of hominids that have walked around this Earth. Most all of them went extinct except us. But the normal and natural state of this Earth is we have various versions of humans walking around at the same time, which is why most of us have some Neanderthal in us. Some of us have some Denisova in us. And some in Washington have a lot more of it. (Laughter) Principle number three: we have to respect other people's choices. Some people will choose to never alter. Some people will choose to alter all. Some people will choose to alter plants but not animals. Some people will choose to alter themselves. Some people will choose to evolve themselves. Diversity is not a bad thing, because even though we think of humans as very diverse, we came so close to extinction that all of us descend from a single African mother and the consequence of that is there's more genetic diversity in 55 African chimpanzees than there are in seven billion humans. Principle number four: we should take about a quarter of the Earth and only let Darwin run the show there. It doesn't have to be contiguous, doesn't have to all be tied together. It should be part in the oceans, part on land. But we should not run every evolutionary decision on this planet. We want to have our evolutionary system running. We want to have Darwin's evolutionary system running. And it's just really important to have these two things running in parallel and not overwhelm evolution. (Applause) Last thing I'll say. This is the single most exciting adventure human beings have been on. This is the single greatest superpower humans have ever had. It would be a crime for you not to participate in this stuff because you're scared of it, because you're hiding from it. You can participate in the ethics. You can participate in the politics. You can participate in the business. You can participate in just thinking about where medicine is going, where industry is going, where we're going to take the world. It would be a crime for all of us not to be aware when somebody shows up at a swimming pool and says one word, just one word, if you don't listen if that word is "lifecode." Thank you very much. (Applause)
Son cosas que hoy damos por sentado. Por eso el código de vida resulta ser un superpoder. Resulta ser un superpoder increíble para cambiar virus, para cambiar plantas, animales, quizá incluso para evolucionar nosotros mismos. Es algo en lo que Steve Gullans y yo hemos estado pensando durante un tiempo. Asumamos algunos riesgos. Al igual que toda tecnología potente como la electricidad, el automóvil, las computadoras, esto potencialmente podría usarse indebidamente. Y eso asusta a mucha gente. Y aplicando estas tecnologías, podemos incluso transformar humanos en quimeras. ¿Recuerdan el mito griego en el que se mezclan animales? Bueno, algunos de estos tratamientos en realidad terminan cambiando el grupo sanguíneo. O pondrán células masculinas en un cuerpo femenino o viceversa, algo que suena absolutamente horrible hasta que uno se da cuenta de que la razón para hacer eso es sustituir la médula ósea durante los tratamientos de cáncer. Así que recibir médula ósea de otra persona, puede cambiar algunos aspectos fundamentales de uno mismo, pero también le salva la vida. Y mientras lo piensan, esto es algo que pasó hace 20 años. Esta es Emma Ott, recientemente admitida en la universidad, donde estudia contabilidad. Practica dos deportes y se gradúa como mejor alumna. Y eso no es particularmente extraordinario, salvo que es el primer ser humano nacido de tres padres. ¿Por qué? Porque ella tenía una enfermedad mitocondrial letal que podría haber heredado. Cuando intercambiamos el ADN de una tercera persona y lo añadimos allí, salvamos la vida de la gente. Pero también se realiza ingeniería de la línea germinal, lo que significa que sus hijos, si tendrá hijos, estarán a salvo y no pasarán por esto. Sus hijos estarán a salvo, y sus nietos estarán a salvo, y se mantendrá esta herencia. Eso pone nerviosa a la gente. Hace 20 años, diversas autoridades dijeron: ¿Por qué no estudiamos esto un tiempo? Hay riesgos al hacer cosas, y hay riesgos al no hacer cosas, porque hay un par de docenas de personas que se salvaron con esta tecnología y lo hemos estado pensando durante los siguientes 20 años. Y mientras lo pensamos, nos tomamos el tiempo para decir: "Quizá deberíamos hacer estudios más largos, quizá deberíamos hacer esto, y aquello", hay consecuencias por actuar, y las hay por no actuar. Como curar enfermedades letales... lo que, por cierto, es totalmente antinatural. Era normal y natural que los humanos fueran diezmados por epidemias masivas de polio, de viruela, tuberculosis. Cuando vacunamos personas, estamos poniendo cosas no naturales en sus cuerpos porque pensamos que el beneficio es mayor que el riesgo. Gracias a que construimos plantas y animales no naturales, podemos alimentar a unas 7000 millones de personas. Podemos crear nuevas formas de vida. Y conforme creamos nuevas formas de vida, de nuevo, suena muy aterrador y terriblemente molesto, hasta que advertimos que esas formas de vida viven en la mesa del comedor. Esas flores que tienen en la mesa del comedor no tienen mucho de naturales, porque las han criado para que tengan ese color, ese tamaño, para que duren una semana. Por lo general no regalamos flores silvestres a los seres queridos porque no duran mucho tiempo. Todo eso trastoca las ideas de Darwin por completo. Vean, durante 4000 millones de años, lo que vivía y moría en este planeta dependía de dos principios: la selección natural y las mutaciones aleatorias. Por eso lo que vivía y moría, lo que estaba estructurado, ahora ha cambiado por completo. Y nosotros creamos este sistema evolutivo completamente en paralelo en el que practicamos selección no natural y mutaciones no aleatorias. Explicaré ambas cosas. Esto es selección natural. Esto es selección no natural. (Risas) Ocurre que empezamos a criar lobos hace miles de años en Asia central para convertirlos en perros. Luego empezamos a convertirlos en perros grandes y en perros chicos. Pero si tomamos uno de los chihuahuas que vemos en los bolsos Hermès en la Quinta Avenida y lo soltamos en la llanura africana podemos observar qué es la selección natural. (Risas) Pocas cosas en el planeta son menos naturales que un campo de maíz. Nunca, bajo ninguna circunstancia, si caminamos por un bosque virgen veremos la misma planta crecer en filas ordenadas al mismo tiempo y sin otras plantas viviendo allí. Cuando cultivamos un campo de maíz, seleccionamos lo que vive y lo que muere. Y lo hacemos mediante selección no natural. Ocurre lo mismo con un trigal o con un campo de arroz. Sucede lo mismo con una ciudad y con una urbanización. De hecho, la mitad de la superficie terrestre tiene un diseño no natural de modo que allí vive y muere lo que nosotros queremos, y por eso no hay osos pardos caminando por el centro de Manhattan. ¿Qué tal esta mutación aleatoria? Bueno, esto es mutación aleatoria. Este es Antonio Alfonseca. También conocido como el Pulpo, su apodo. Fue el lanzador revelación del año 2000. Y tenía una mutación aleatoria que resultó en seis dedos en cada mano, algo muy útil si uno es lanzador. (Risas) ¿Qué tal la mutación no aleatoria? Una mutación no aleatoria es la cerveza. Es el vino. Es el yogur. ¿Cuántas veces caminando por el bosque encontraron queso completamente natural? ¿O yogur natural? Hemos diseñado estas cosas. Ahora, lo interesante es que conocemos mejor el tema. Encontramos una de las herramientas más poderosos de edición de genes, la CRISPR, dentro del yogur. Y cuando empezamos a diseñar células, producimos ocho de los 10 primeros productos farmacéuticos, incluyendo el utilizado para tratar la artritis, que es el fármaco de mayor venta, Humira. Este código de vida en realidad es un superpoder. Realmente es una forma de programar cosas y no hay nada que nos vaya a cambiar más que este código de vida. Mientras piensan en el código de vida, pensemos en cinco principios, para empezar, y me encantaría que me sugieran más. El principio número uno: tenemos que asumir la responsabilidad por estas cosas. La razón por la que tenemos que asumir la responsabilidad es que estamos a cargo. Estas no son mutaciones aleatorias. Es lo que estamos haciendo, lo que estamos eligiendo. No es algo que "ocurrió". No ocurrió por azar. No es producto de otra persona. Nosotros lo diseñamos y sigue la regla de la empresa Pottery Barn: lo rompes, lo pagas. Principio número dos: tenemos que reconocer y celebrar su diversidad. Ha habido por lo menos 33 versiones de homínidos que han caminado por el planeta. La mayoría se extinguió, salvo nosotros. Sin embargo, en el estado normal y natural del planeta hay diferentes versiones de seres humanos caminando al mismo tiempo, razón por la que la mayoría de nosotros tenemos algo de neandertales, otros tenemos algo de denisovanos, y algunos en Washington tienen mucho más de cada uno. (Risas) El principio número tres: tenemos que respetar las decisiones de otras personas. Algunas personas optan por no alterar nada, otras por modificarlo todo. Algunas personas optarán por alterar las plantas, pero no los animales, otras por alterarse a sí mismos o simplemente evolucionar. La diversidad no es algo malo, porque a pesar de que pensamos que los seres humanos somos muy diversos, estuvimos tan cerca de la extinción que todos descendemos de una sola madre africana, y la consecuencia de eso es que hay más diversidad genética en 55 chimpancés africanos que en 7000 millones de seres humanos. Principio número cuatro: deberíamos tomar una cuarta parte de la Tierra y dejar a Darwin que haga lo suyo allí. No tiene que ser contiguo o todo interconectado y debería cubrir parte agua y parte tierra, pero no deberíamos involucrarnos en cada decisión evolutiva del planeta. Queremos que nuestro sistema evolutivo funcione y el sistema evolutivo de Darwin también. Y es muy importante tener estas dos cosas funcionando en paralelo y no abrumar a la evolución. (Aplausos) Lo último que diré es que esta es la aventura más emocionante emprendida por los humanos. Este es el mayor superpoder que hemos tenido los seres humanos. Sería un crimen no participar en esto por tener miedo o querer evitar el tema. Pueden opinar sobre su ética. Pueden participar en la política. Pueden participar en el negocio. Pueden participar solo pensando hacia dónde va la medicina, la industria, y cómo controlaremos el mundo. Sería un crimen para todos nosotros hacer caso omiso a alguien que se presenta en una piscina y dice una frase, una sola frase; sería un crimen si no escuchan aquella frase que es "código de vida". Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)